Finding Aid for Mortimer E. Cooley Papers 1873-1944
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mortimer E. Cooley Papers
1873-1944
Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.
Dean of the College of Engineering of the University of Michigan; correspondence, letter books, appraisals and reports, lectures, blueprints, newspaper clippings, photographs, and other materials concerning his activities as dean of the College of Engineering, engineer for the U.S.S. Yosemite in the Spanish American War, chairman of the Block Signal and Train Control Board, Democratic candidate for the U.S. Senate in 1924, and coordinator for the P.W.A. in Michigan in 1933-1935; also genealogical materials on the Cooley family.
851012 Aa 2; AC;Ac
66.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
7 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection came primarily from Mortimer Cooley (donor no. 1755 ) and from the College of Engineering (donor no. 1884 ). A smaller portion of materials came from the Alumni Association (donor no. 1617 ).
The collection is open for research.
Mortimer E. Cooley was born in Canandaigua, New York on March 28, 1855. He graduated from the United States Naval Academy in 1878 as an engineer cadet. He advanced to the rank of assistant engineer in 1880, then in 1881, he was ordered to the University of Michigan as professor of steam engineering and iron shipbuilding. Cooley resigned from the navy in 1885 though he did serve a brief tour of volunteer naval duty during the Spanish-American War as chief engineer of the blockade ship, "Yosemite." In 1904 Cooley was made dean of the Department of Engineering and in 1913 he also selected as dean of the newly combined Departments of Engineering and Architecture (renamed in 1915 the College of Engineering and Architecture). Cooley retired as dean in 1928 but remained active at the University and in other capacities until his death in 1944.
Cooley made his mark as a expert in the area of public utilities, helping to develop standardized and meaningful methods for evaluating public utilities. In 1900, at the request of Governor Hazen S. Pingree, Cooley collaborated with U-M economist Henry Carter Adams in devising a viable and scientific method of determining railroad valuation for purposes of taxation. Because of the significance of this work, both Wisconsin and Minnesota looked to Cooley for help in developing their own systems of railroad evaluation. In addition, Cooley served as long-time advisor for the Interstate Commerce Commission and was its first consultant in its nationwide railroad appraisal program.
Cooley ran unsuccessfully for the United States Senate from Michigan in 1924. Among other issues, Cooley campaigned on the need for conservation and efficiency of resource use. Cooley believed that there should be more technically trained individuals in the Congress, including engineers and economist, not just attorneys and professional politicians. During the New Deal, Cooley was named state engineer for the Public Works Administration.
Cooley died August 25, 1944.
The Mortimer E. Cooley papers consists of correspondence, subject files, personal materials, and photographs detailing the professional career and activities of a distinguished engineering educator. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Topical Files; University of Michigan and College of Engineering materials; Genealogical and Miscellaneous; Arbitration, appraisal, and consultation files; Photographs; Naval Logs; and Testimonial and celebratory materials. Box 47 was eliminated during 2001 reprocessing.
Subjects:
American Engineering Council.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Cooley family.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Engineering--Study and teaching.; Engineers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Log-books.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1922-1928.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; New Deal, 1933-1939--Michigan.; Public utilities--Valuation.; Public welfare--Michigan.; Railroads--Valuation.; Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education (U.S.); Spanish-American War, 1898.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1924.Elections, 1924.; United States--Politics and government--1923-1929.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; United States--Politics and government--1929-1933.; United States. Public Works Administration.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.); Yosemite (Cruiser)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Bridges.; Buildings--Michigan--Detroit.; Cooley family.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Davis, Joseph Baker, 1845-1920.; Detroit (Mich.)--Buildings.; Engineering.; Fort Shelby Hotel (Detroit, Mich.); Manistee River (Mich.); Michigan Union.; Parades and processions.; Spanish-American War, 1898.; University of Michigan--Buildings.Buildings.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1901-1910.StudentsSocial life and customs1901-1910.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence
  Correspondence (44.3 linear ft.; 1873-1944) is the largest series in the collection and documents Cooley's extensive responsibilities as dean of the College of Engineering, as appraiser of railroads and other public utilities for Michigan and consultant, and as a leader in the field of engineering education.
  - Undated, 1873-1888 (Box 1)
  - 1889-August 1891 (Box 2)
  - September 1891-October 1893 (Box 3)
  - November 1893-October 1894 (Box 4)
  - November 1894-March 1896 (Box 5)
  - April 1896-August 1897 (Box 6)
  - September 1897-April 1899 (Box 7)
  - May 1899-March 1901 (Box 8)
  - April 1901-November 1901 (Box 9)
  - December 1901-July 1902 (Box 10)
  - August 1902-April 1903 (Box 11)
  - May 1903-April 1904 (Box 12)
  - May 1904-July 1905 (Box 13)
  - August 1905-December 1906 (Box 14)
  - January 1907-January 1908 (Box 15)
  - February 1908-December 1908 (Box 16)
  - January 1909-January 1910 (Box 17)
  - February 1910-February 1911 (Box 18)
  - March 1911-February 1912 (Box 19)
  - March 1912-May 1913 (Box 20)
  - June 1913-September 1914 (Box 21)
  - October 1914-August 1915 (Box 22)
  - September 1915-May 1916 (Box 23)
  - June 1916-March 1917 (Box 24)
  - April 1917-March 1918 (Box 25)
  - April 1918-February 1919 (Box 26)
  - March 1919-December 1919 (Box 27)
  - January 1920-November 1920 (Box 28)
  - December 1920-October 1921 (Box 29)
  - November 1921-August 1922 (Box 30)
  - September 1922-June 1923 (Box 31)
  - July 1923-July 1924 (Box 32)
  - August 1924-October 1925 (Box 33)
  - November 1925-December 1926 (Box 34)
  - January 1927-December 1928 (Box 35)
  - January 1929-June 1930 (Box 36)
  - July 1930-April 1932 (Box 37)
  - May 1932-December 1933 (Box 38)
  - January 1934-December 1935 (Box 39)
  - January 1936-August 1937 (Box 40)
  - September 1937-March 1939 (Box 41)
  - April 1939-September 1940 (Box 42)
  - October 1940-November 1941 (Box 43)
  - December 1941-March 1943 (Box 44)
  - April 1943-1944 (Box 45)
- Topical files, 1880s-1940s
  Topical Files (1.7 linear ft.; 1880s-1940s) is an alphabetically arranged series of files on Cooley, his organizational affiliations, and his other projects and interests. Of note are those files from his work with the American Engineering Council (1919-1925); information about his unsuccessful campaign for the US Senate in 1924; and his service during the Spanish-American War.
  - American Engineering Council, 1919-1925; 8 folders (Box 45)
  - Ann Arbor Scientific Club (Box 45)
  - Belle Isle Bridge Project (Box 45)
  - Biographical material
    - General, 2 folders (Box 45)
    - Clippings, 2 folders (Box 45)
  - Canadaigua, New York, lands (Box 45)
  - Election of, 1924; 3 folders (Box 45)
  - Hudson Motor Car Company (blueprints of construction project) (Box 46)
  - Kaiser (abdication) (Box 46)
    (announced through seismograph records)
  - Letterbook, 1880s (Box 46)
  - Masonic miscellanea (Box 46)
  - Memoranda books (selection) (Box 46)
  - Michigan Naval Reserves (U.S.S. Yantic) (Box 46)
  - Mortimer Cooley Foundation (Box 46)
  - Packard Motor Car Co (Box 46)
  - Penn State U. (Box 46)
    (includes letters of remembrance by former students)
  - Political miscellanea (Box 46)
  - Production Engineering research (Box 46)
  - Scientific blacksmith (Cooley autobiography) (Box 46)
    (background information and correspondence with collaborator Vivien Keatley)
  - Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education (Box 46)
  - Spanish-American War service, 3 folders (Box 46)
  - Weldon Gold and Copper Company, 2 folders (Box 46)
  - World's Columbian Exposition, 1893; 2 folders (Box 46)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 46)
  - Box eliminated during 2001 reprocessing. (Box 47)
- University of Michigan and College of Engineering, 1905-1926
  University of Michigan and College of Engineering materials (1 linear ft.; 1905-1926) is a miscellanea of files largely on detailing the administration of the college and the particulars of engineering education. The researcher should note that the records of the College of Engineering during Cooley's deanship are also located at the Bentley Library.
  - Athletic Association (Box 48)
  - Denison, Charles Simeon (Box 48)
  - Engineering, College of
    - Engineering at the University of Michigan (Box 48)
    - Curricula (history of) (Box 48)
    - Engineering buildings (Box 48)
    - Engineering education and curricula (Box 48)
    - Engineering research, proposed department, 1919 (Box 48)
    - Engineering Research dept
      - Circulars, 1923-1926 (Box 48)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 48)
    - Enrollment (Box 48)
    - Enrollment, space, credit hour report, 1920 (Box 48)
    - Graduates and alumni (Box 48)
    - Mechanical Engineering dept (Box 48)
    - Mines, School of Mines (Box 48)
    - Nautical school, proposed, 1909 (Box 48)
    - Summer School committee (Box 48)
    - Surveying dept (Box 48)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 48)
  - Goddard, L.W. (Box 48)
    (includes 1883 stereocard of students outside engineering building)
  - Greene. Charles E. Greene memorial tablet dedication, 1905 (Box 48)
  - Michigan Union Building (Box 48)
  - President, selection of (Box 48)
  - Sigma Phi (Box 48)
  - Student Council, 1911-1915 (Box 48)
  - Wilson, C.E. (professor of mechanical engineering) (Box 48)
  - Wood, De Volson (Box 48)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 48)
- Genealogical and Miscellaneous, 1889-1935
  Genealogical and Miscellaneous (12 linear ft.; 1889-1935) consists mainly of materials accumulated by Cooley on the genealogy of his family. There are also some letterbooks and scrapbooks on his work with the PWA during the depression.
  - Genealogical material concerning the Cooley family (Box 50)
  - Genealogical material concerning the Cooley family (Box 51)
    (continued)
  - Genealogical material concerning the Cooley family (Box 52)
  - Genealogical material concerning the Cooley family (Box 53)
  - Genealogical material concerning the Cooley family (Box 54)
  - Genealogical material concerning the Cooley family (Box 55)
  - Genealogical material concerning the Cooley family (Box 56)
  - Genealogical material concerning the Cooley family (Box 57)
  - Letterbooks, 1889-1896 (Box 58)
  - Letterbooks, 1896-1900 (Box 59)
  - Notes on Water Wheels by M.E. Cooley (Box 59)
  - Scrapbooks concerning P.W.A. activities, August-October 1933 (Box 59)
  - Scrapbooks concerning P.W.A. activities, November 1933-1935 (Box 60)
  - Speeches (Box 61)
  - Writings (miscellaneous) (Box 61)
  - Christmas cards (Box 61)
- Arbitration, appraisal, and consultation files, 1893-1915
  Arbitration, appraisal, and consultation files (6 linear ft.; 1893-1915) include information on Cooley's work with railroad and other public utilities appraisals. Cooley did work both for the state of Michigan and outside of the state. The researcher should note that Cooley's work in appraising Michigan's railroads for purposes of taxation is documented in the records of the Michigan Board of State Tax Commissioners also located at the Bentley Library.
  - Minneapolis General Electric Company (Box 62)
  - Cleveland Railway Company (Box 62)
    (1908 appraisal)
  - Beckwith Estate, Dowagiac (Box 62)
  - Michigan United Railways
    - Kalamazoo (Box 62)
    - Battle Creek (Box 62)
    - Lansing (Box 62)
    - Jackson (Box 62)
  - Detroit Edison Company (Box 62)
    (1915 appraisal)
  - Milwaukee Electric Railway and Light Company (Box 62)
    (1909 appraisal)
  - Redwing (Minn.) Gas, Light and Power Company (Box 62)
  - Flint Electric Company (Box 62)
    (1910 appraisal)
  - Ann Arbor Waterworks, 1910 (Box 62)
  - Flint City Waterworks Company (1903 arbitration) (Box 63)
  - Block Signal and Train Control Board (Box 63)
  - Metropolitan West Side (Chicago) Elevated Railway, 1908 (Box 63)
  - Grand Rapids Muskegon Power Co. (1910); and Bay City Power Co (Box 64)
  - Michigan Railroad Reappraisal (Box 64)
  - Boyne City, Gaylord and Alpena Railroad Company (appraisal) (Box 65)
  - Detroit United Railroad appraisal, 2 folders (Box 65)
  - Interstate Commerce Commission miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 65)
  - Chicago City Railway Co (Box 49)
  - Detroit Citizens Street Railway Company, 1899 (Box 49)
  - General Motors. Board of Appraisal and Arbitration (Box 49)
  - Going Concern Value: Isaac G. Johnson Co (Box 49)
  - Michigan Railroad Commission (Box 49)
  - Public Utilities Properties Appraised or Investigated by MEC (Box 49)
  - Railroad appraisals (various) (Box 49)
  - Stirling Boiler co. patent case, 1893-1895; 3 folders (Box 49)
  - Telephone appraisal, 2 folders (Box 49)
  - Valves (Box 49)
    (1911 patent case)
  - Miscellaneous patents (Box 49)
- Photographs, 1.5 linear feet
  The Photograph series (1.5 linear ft.) includes portraits; family portraits and homestead photos collected for his published Cooley family genealogy; University of Michigan photos, including buildings, classes and students, and laboratory facilities; and other buildings, individuals, and engineering projects.
  - Cooley, Albert family (Box 66)
  - Cooley, Eugene family (Box 66)
  - Cooley, George Solomon family and homestead (Box 66)
  - Cooley, Lyman family (Box 66)
  - Cooley, Mortimer Elwyn. Portraits (Box 66)
  - Cooley, Mortimer Elwyn. With colleagues and acquaintances (including J.B. Davis (Box 66)
  - Cooley, Mortimer Elwyn family (Box 66)
  - Cooley, Thomas (1778-1847) family (Box 66)
  - Cooley, Thomas McIntyre (1824-1898) family (Box 66)
  - Cooley family (other individuals and groups) (Box 66)
  - Homesteads and miscellaneous illustrations for Cooley Genealogy (Box 66)
  - Michigan. University. Campus and buildings (Box 66)
  - Michigan. University. Classes and commencements (Box 66)
  - Michigan. University. Laboratories (Box 66)
  - Michigan. University. School of Engineering. Early buildings (Box 66)
  - Michigan. University. Union County Fair Parade (Box 66)
  - Miscellaneous (include Fort Shelby Hotel in Detroit under construction ), circa 1918 (Box 66)
  - U.S. Naval Academy (Cooley portraits, class portraits); U.S. Steamer Yosemite, Spanish-American War Service (Box 66)
  - Mortimer Cooley Bridge (Box 67)
  - Group and class photos (Box 67)
  - Portraits, Cooley with others (Box 67)
- Naval Logs
  Naval Logs (1890; 1898-1899; 1906; 5 oversize volumes) are from the U.S. Steamer Yosemite (and others) and are mainly from the period of the Spanish-American War.
  - Steam log (rough) of U.S. Steamer Yosemite, 1898; 2 volumes
  - Log of US Steamer Yosemite, May-June 1899; photostatic copy (Box 67)
  - Steam log (rough) of U.S. Steamer Don Juan de Austria, 1906 (Box 67)
  - Steam log (rough) of U.S. Steamer Yantic, 1890 (Box 67)
- Testimonial and celebratory materials
  Testimonial and celebratory materials (2 oversize volumes and 1 oversize folder) includes scrapbooks created for Cooley on birthdays and other celebrations. Included are letters of remembrance and congratulations and other memorabilia.
  - Scrapbook containing correspondence and other miscellanea upon occasion of a testimonial dinner in MEC's honor, 1923 (Box 67)
  - Scrapbook containing correspondence and other miscellanea upon the occasion of MEC's 80th birthday, 1935 (Box 67)
  - Various citations and diplomas, 17 items (Folder 1)